Plymouth Congregational Church (Syracuse, N.Y.) Records
Plymouth Congregational Church (Syracuse, N.Y.) Records
1853-1999
Plymouth Congregational Church (Syracuse, N.Y.)
0.5 linear ft.
Meeting minutes for board of trustees, church society record books, church reports, Ecclesiastical Society material, and published material relating to Plymouth Congregational Church in Syracuse, New York. The majority of the collection is either microfilm or photocopies.
2963269
Biographical History
Plymouth Congregational Church of Syracuse, New York was organized on September 24, 1853. Some members were fearful that it might be a failure, since an earlier Congregational Church had disbanded. The original membership numbered 30, and at a meeting held in the rooms of the Park Institute (corner of Genesee and Fayette Streets) it was stated that "while it should be purely Congregational in its character, it should embody in its organization and government the distinctive characteristics of [Henry Ward Beecher's] Plymouth Church of Brooklyn, New York."
By 1856, a chapel on Madison Street was dedicated and in 1858 the congregation, now incorporated, bought the lot on which the chapel stood. They furnished it and made plans for a brick church, to be completed by the following summer. In July of 1859 the new building was completed; on August 3, 1859 the church was dedicated and Rev. Mr. Strieby installed as pastor for the congregation, now grown to 261.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Plymouth Congregational Church (Syracuse, N.Y.) Records consists of church records, including legal, financial, organizational, historical, and administrative. The vast majority of the material is either photocopies or microfilm; there is almost no original material in the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by subject; within each folder, material is arranged chronologically.
Related Material
has numerous collection related to church and clergy in Central New York. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; New York State; Plymouth Congregational Church (Syracuse, N.Y.) -- Archives.; Congregational Church (Syracuse, N.Y.) -- History.; Syracuse (N.Y.) -- Religious life and customs.; Church records.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); Reports.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Plymouth Congregational Church (Syracuse, N.Y.), 1964, 1968, 1970, 1999.
Inventory
- Subject files
  - Annual reports, 1999; original (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees
    - Minutes, 1853-1950; microfilm
    - Minutes, 1950-1966; photocopies; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Certificate of incorporation, 1858; photocopies (Box 1)
  - Church Report books, 1891-1921; microfilm
  - Church Society record books, 1858-1940; microfilm
  - Correspondence, 1894; photocopies (Box 1)
  - Ecclesiastical Society, 1940; 1952; photocopies (Box 1)
  - Financial records, 1899; 1950-1954; photocopies (Box 1)
  - Insurance record, 1953; photocopies (Box 1)
  - Legal documents, 1951; 1953; photocopies (Box 1)
  - Manuals, 1853; 1883; photocopies (Box 1)
  - Plymouth Church Record, 1873-1874; photocopies (Box 1)
  - "Years of Plymouth", 1963; 1998; church history; photocopy of typescript plus later addenda (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1887; 1999; original clipping, photocopy of "Act relating to the property of extinct or disbanded churches" (Box 1)